Good morning.
Homonym what? Ad hominem means when you make an argument where you
attack the character of the person you're disagreeing with rather than actually
engaging with the substance of the facts which are being debated. So
it's a logical fallacy to say that oh just because he's a
thief, so if he's a thief, then therefore I don't care what
he has to say about, you know, whether or not the school
board should meet on Tuesdays or Thursdays, like actually those two things
have nothing to do with each other and devaluing someone's opinion just
because of who they are sometimes is important and to a certain
extent is a meaningful and reasonable thing to
do but cross where you discredit a witness, right I was just
going to say discredit a witness, right.
But so right,
so discrediting a witness is one thing because it means that you're
taking them out of credibility for the other things that they say.
In a case of sort of an ad hominem attack, the point
is that I'm not actually going to engage with what you've said,
I'll say oh it's a problem because of something else you did
or something else you said and actually not engaging with the substance
of your argument. Good morning everyone.
Today is February 21st, it's the 6th of אדר. Adar. Tomorrow is
משה רבינו's Moshe Rabbeinu יארצייט, yahrtzeit, 7th of אדר, Adar, and we
are going to pick up on עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah ל"ו עמוד
ב lamed vav amud bet toward the bottom, you're going to have
to give me a second to find the exact spot.
We were in the middle, let's start
from where
was it?
Okay,
we were sort of in the middle of all this back and
forth well towards the end of all this back and forth about
what was it exactly that the students of שמאי Shammai and הלל
Hillel had enacted regarding בנותיהם binoteihem that is there was some kind
of a rabbinic law about about intermarriage or inter-faith something
to do with with relationships between men and women. We were unclear
a little bit as to what the exact substance of that rabbinic
law was because it seemed like certain aspects of the law against
intermarriage were of a biblical origin and certain things were from הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai and so there was a little bit
of a question about what are we actually talking about.
And so and so we're going to pick up where it says
on ל"ו עמוד ב lamed vav amud bet דאמר רבי יוחנן משום
רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotsadak
it's in the fifth wide line of ל"ו עמוד ב. lamed vav
amud bet. So this is sort of in the middle of this
whole discussion but basically there had been a lot of back and
forth about well what actually was established by the students of שמאי
Shammai and הלל Hillel because there are other rabbinic laws which were
established earlier like with the בית דין Beit Din of דוד, David,
the בית דין Beit Din of שם, Shem, the son of נח,
Noah, very interesting sort of rabbinic construction to see rabbinic activity on
the laws of בני נח bnei Noach as well and
and things like and the בני חשמונאים Bnei Chashmonaim during the during
the Hasmonean dynasty as well. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan quoted רבי
שמעון בן יהוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotsadak רמז לייחוד מן התורה מנין?
remez l'yichud min haTorah minayin? How do we know that there is
a hint or an allusion reference to the idea of ייחוד yichud
the prohibition of a man and woman being together in private even
if there's no actual sexual activity between them mentioned even or hinted
to even in the תורה Torah usually רמז remez means it's really
a rabbinic law which is being alluded to or provided with a
mnemonic in the תורה. Torah. שנאמר Shene'emar the פסוק pasuk says כי
יסיתך אחיך בן אמך ki yesitcha achicha ben imecha וכי בן אם
מסית בן אב אינו מסית? v'chi ben em mesit ben av eino
mesit?
So it says that your your mother's son the your brother who
is the son of your mother will seduce you to follow עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. It's interesting here the ייחוד yichud is not about
a sexual encounter but is about someone convincing you in private that
you should really worship עבודה זרה avodah zarah and it says that
it's your brother the son of your mother. So does only a
maternal brother seduce you but בן אב אינו מסית? ben av eino
mesit? But a paternal brother does not? אלא בן מתייחד עם אמו.
Ela ben mityached im imo. There's an allusion to the idea that
the exception to the law of ייחוד yichud is that parents and
children a son with his mother is permissible ואין אחר מתייחד עם
כל העריות שבתורה. v'ein acher mityached im kol ha'arayot shebaTorah. And no
one else is allowed to have ייחוד yichud with anyone else from
the תורה Torah now does this mean a father with a daughter?
I think generally we assume yes but these are these are important
questions to consider particularly you know in circumstances where you know normal
living conditions you're going to have children who live at home and
they're going to be with their parents and they it shouldn't be
a ייחוד yichud problem and we would hope obviously that there is
no sexual tension between parents and children.
Okay.
So ייחוד yichud דאורייתא de'oraita דאשת איש. d'eshet ish.
So one second, so if that's a sense that oh maybe there's
a sense of ייחוד yichud that's actually דאורייתא de'oraita then we'll say
דאשת איש d'eshet ish that actually the דאורייתא de'oraita principle of ייחוד
yichud only applies to a married woman. Then the עריות, arayot, the
other forbidden sexual relationships in the תורה, Torah, the prohibition of ייחוד
yichud is at a level of דרבנן d'rabbanan that was established relatively
early on, and then the later, right, ואתא בדוד וגזר אפילו על
ייחוד דפנויה, va-ata b'David v'gazar afilu al yichud d'penuyah, and the בית
דין Beit Din of דוד David created a rabbinic law even against
having ייחוד yichud with an unmarried woman, that is an unmarried man,
unmarried woman, or even a married man with an unmarried woman, but
that that was seen as risky and potentially problematic from a promiscuity
angle or from a relationships angle even though it actually there's no
prohibition involved, right? An unmarried woman could be very well, could under
certain circumstances at least she could be marrying this man, so so
there's no reason why the ייחוד yichud would be problematic, and in
fact part of our marriage ceremony is to include a ייחוד. yichud.
Yeah.
Well and in fact by having ביאה, bi'ah, they at least in
תורה Torah law she could have actually become married.
Of course, that's what I'm trying to say, which is that there's
no prohibition that's being avoided, but the thing that is being avoided
or that was sensed as a greater safeguard against sexual encounters, which
which in this circumstance is seen as a healthy and important thing.
So ואתו תלמידי שמאי ובית הלל, v'atu talmidei Shammai v'Beit Hillel, so
students of בית שמאי ובית הלל, Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel, גזרו אפילו
על ייחוד דעובדי כוכבים, gazaru afilu al yichud d'avodat kochavim, and then
the students of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel created the laws of
ייחוד yichud which would even apply between a Jewish man and a
non-Jewish woman, that is originally or we would say we would have
hopefully have said there was a sense that there was no risk
of sexual impropriety between men and women, here a Jewish man and
a non-Jewish woman, because we would so hope we would say that
a Jewish man would have no business being involved with this woman.
What about the other way around?
The other way around as far as I understand the ייחוד yichud
prohibition in the תלמוד Talmud is generally framed as the man's problem,
and so it wouldn't make sense for them to say it as
a problem for a Jewish woman to have
ייחוד yichud with a non-Jewish man.
But we considered for larger things like when we considered before about
rape.
Right, we were talking about rape and other things, so in those
kinds of contexts I would think similarly you would have the same
kind of a same kind of a problem. Okay,
fine. So now we go into sort of the next topic which
was that our list of גזירות gezeirot that had been mentioned had
said they made a גזירה gezeirah because of פיתן ושמנן משום יינן,
pitanu shemanan mishum yeinan, they made a law against oil and bread
because of
wine, and the יינן משום בנותיהם, yeinam mishum b'noteihem, and the wine
is because of their daughters, the non-Jewish women, and here the reference
we've finally reached a conclusion which was that that גזירה gezeirah which
was established by בית שמאי ובית הלל Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel was
the prohibition on ייחוד yichud between a Jewish man and a non-Jewish
woman because the prohibition on marriage had already been established previously, okay.
And then they said and further ודבר אחר משום דבר אחר. v'davar
acher mishum davar acher. No, and the בנותיהם b'noteihem is because of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But then בנותיהם b'noteihem is because of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, and then also דבר אחר משום דבר אחר, davar
acher mishum davar acher, and they made some other גזירה gezeirah which
is left unspecified because of some other reason which is left unspecified.
So why did they have to use so much euphemism? So now
we're going to clarify what's being talked about there, and this comes
up in other places where it's dealt with a little bit differently,
but let's at least read what it says here.
Okay, so מאי על דבר אחר משום דבר אחר? mai al davar
acher mishum davar acher? What does it mean they made a rabbinic
law about something else because of something else? Okay you really have
to keep this in your mouth. Okay. Okay, אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק,
amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said
גזרו על תינוק עובד כוכבים שייטמא בזיבה, gazaru al tinok oved kochavim
she'itamei b'zivah, they made a law that a male child who is
of an idolatrous
persuasion that such a child יטמא בזיבה yitamei b'zivah is טמא tamei
as a זב, zav, that is he sits on a chair or
whatever he will become טמא tamei שלא יהא תינוק ישראל רגיל אצלו
she'lo yeihei tinok Yisrael ragil etzlo to prevent intermingling between Jewish and
non-Jewish young boys במשכב זכור b'mishkav zachor to prevent homosexual relationships between
the children or between adults and children. As far as we know
from בית שני Bayit Sheni period we have many sources both from
outside of our tradition as well as inside of our tradition that
criticize the rabbinic class from being very into טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah
and not into anything else, that we have very powerful ברייתות baraitas
quoted in תוספתא Tosefta in יומא Yoma I think the discussion right
that one of the כהנים kohanim stabbed another of the כהנים kohanim
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the father of the young
man who had been stabbed said hurry hurry up quickly take the
knife out before he dies so that it won't become טמא. tamei.
Wow. So he had no sense of his son's death and that
a crime had been committed in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in
this regard and that's a very shocking tale that's meant to reorient
our priorities in that regard. Charlie, yeah.
And as you might expect שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz makes it תינוק גוי. tinok
goy.
תינוק גוי, tinok goy, well no so the text right every time
it says עובד כוכבים oved kochavim basically every time it says עובד...
oved... עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, the text correctly is probably גוי. goy.
That’s just how it is, but I’m reading from the גמרא Gemara
that I have in front of me. What does תינוק tinok mean
in this case? תינוק tinok means a child, not a baby. Like
what? Right. Oh, so we’re going to see what age. It’s going
to come up. It’s going to be the age of nine years,
nine years old, nine years and one day. Okay, דאמר רב זירא,
d'amar Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav Zeira said: צער גדול היה אצל
רבי אסי, tza’ar gadol haya etzel Rabbi Assi, I had a great
problem with רבי אסי, Rabbi Assi, ורבי אסי אצל רבי יוחנן, v’Rabbi
Assi etzel Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי אסי Rabbi Assi had a problem
with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן אצל רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yochanan
etzel Rabbi Yannai, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had a problem with
רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, ורבי ינאי אצל רבי נתן בן עמרם, v’Rabbi
Yannai etzel Rabbi Natan ben Amram, and רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai had
it with רבי נתן בן עמרם. Rabbi Natan ben Amram. These are
like each student to teacher. ורבי נתן בן עמרם אצל רבי, v’Rabbi
Natan ben Amram etzel Rebbi, and רבי נתן בן עמרם Rabbi Natan
ben Amram had a problem from רבי. Rebbi. Now the question, interesting
thing here is: is רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai a direct student of
רבי Rebbi or is he an indirect student of רבי? Rebbi? Okay,
תינוק עובד כוכבים מאימתי מיטמא בזיבה? tinok oveid kochavim me'ematai mitamei be'zivah?
They had the question: from what age, at what age does this
child become considered a זב? zav? Okay, ואמר לי בן יומו, v’amar
li ben yomo, they told me from the day of birth, right,
the day he’s born. וכשבאתי אצל רבי חייא, u’keshebati etzel Rabbi Chiya,
but when I came to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, אמר לי בן
תשע שנים ויום אחד. amar li ben tesha shanim v'yom echad. רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya said it was from nine years old and one
day, that is nine years old. וכשבאתי והרציתי דברי לפני רבי, u’keshebati
v’hirtzeiti devarai lifnei Rebbi, when I came back and quoted רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya to רבי, Rebbi, אמר לי הנח דברי ואחוז דברי רבי
חייא. amar li hanach devarai v'echoz divrei Rabbi Chiya. רבי Rebbi said:
ignore what I said, listen to רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. It’s very
interesting, right? We know that רבי, יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, was
very humble with regard to his traditions, with regard to his own
teachings. He’s the one who always says אומר אני, omer ani, he’s
like puts himself, you know, he lowers his own position. So here
too he has רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, his colleague, even maybe somewhat
junior colleague, has what he considers a better tradition or more reasonable
position on this question. Yeah.
Is this the רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya who put together the תוספתא?
Tosefta? תוספתא, Tosefta, yeah, it’s the same רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. So
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is a bit of a junior colleague of
רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi and רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi, here still accepts his position, very interesting. Okay.
Can you say: what is this צער גדול? tza’ar gadol?
The צער גדול tza’ar gadol is that I didn’t know which was
the correct opinion, whether to follow from the day of birth or
from nine years old. Nine years old we know is sort of
in general the cutoff for when a boy becomes a man in
terms of הלכתי halachic for sexual questions, which is very interesting why
the cutoff is different than for legal maturity in other regards. I
think it has something to do with criminalizing certain aspects of pedophilia.
Obviously חז"ל Chazal didn’t anticipate the same extent that we’ve gone to
today, but I think there’s something there of that.
Is it also when he’s able to be called a child?
Well, I think it’s very rare that any boy, even in their
time and certainly in our time, has reached puberty by nine years
old. Right, the presumption of puberty is thirteen. But the idea is
that from nine years old already there’s something, there’s enough maturity or
enough physical development in some way that a sexual act is legally
considered a sexual act from that age. Defines adulthood, right? It’s not
adulthood, right? Adulthood we would still say is thirteen. So this is
a pre-adulthood that has certain legal
consequences, yeah? Yeah. Pederasty was extremely common in the Greco-Roman world, and
I think that's part of what חז"ל Chazal have... obviously it’s certainly
not the same mindset that we have today, but I think it’s
at least for their time certainly it was very forward-thinking and you
know we continue thinking forward.
Okay. דאמר, d'amar, so what did רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya say? דאמר:
תינוק עובד כוכבים מאימתי מיטמא בזיבה? d'amar: tinok oveid kochavim me'ematai mitamei
be'zivah? At what age does a non-Jewish child convey impurity like a
זב? zav? בן תשע שנים ויום אחד. ben tesha shanim v'yom echad.
From age nine and one day. We’ll turn to ל"ז עמוד א'.
Lamed Zayin Amud Aleph. הואיל וראוי לביאה מיטמא נמי בזיבה. ho’il v’ra’ui
l’bi’ah mitamei nami be'zivah. We create a comparison or an analogy between
the fact that the sexual relationship is considered legally meaningful and the
equivalent laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah that there’s some connection. Now
is זיבה, zivah, זב, zav, is not exactly connected to sex in
any way explicitly in the תורה, Torah, though there have been some
suggestions that זב zav is some kind of a gonorrhea or something
like that, so that may be involved here as well, that if
the... that we’re creating a fake זב zav status for non-Jewish boys,
or non-Jewish men of all ages from age nine going forward, and
therefore that in some way that’s somehow connected to sexual maturity as
well. אמר רבינא הלכך, amar Ravina hilkach, so רבינא Ravina said הלכך,
hilkach, התינוקת עובדת כוכבים בת שלוש שנים ויום אחד. ha-tinoket ovedet kochavim
bat shalosh shanim v'yom echad.
So רבינא Ravina says analogously for a non-Jewish girls and non-Jewish women
we should assume that they have the status of a זבה zavah
from age three years old, because we know that while for boys
the sexual cutoff is age nine, for girls it’s from age three.
All sorts of reasons why that is. But the point here then
is that analogously to this law about זב, zav, which remember was
predicated on a presumption or a concern about male homosexuality, here is
now being extended as well by רבינא Ravina much later in the
period of אמוראים Amoraim to apply to women as well, sort of
a general extension of the laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah to
include non-Jews as well.
So because she's considered at that age to be sexually within the
within the law for sexual matters, so she should be considered as
a זבה Zava as well. So פשיטא, pshita, so isn't that an
obvious statement? מהו דתימא האי ידע לארגולי. mahu detema hai yada le-argulei.
Maybe you would say, why should we, why did רבינא Ravina have
to even teach this? Is because I might have thought that a
nine-year-old boy is able to to entice or seduce another man or
another boy, והא לא ידעה לארגולי, ve-ha lo yada'ah le-argulei, but a
three-year-old girl has no no sexual drive, has no interest in any
of this, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, the point that רבינא
Ravina is saying is that we across the board create this comparison
and analogy between them even though it's less, much less likely or
much less reasonable to make the same kind of assumption. Okay.
So does this three year old only apply for girls, only apply
for non-Jewish girls? Right.
If for a Jewish girl or Jewish women, the assumption would be
whenever she is a נדה, Niddah, she is a נדה, Niddah, whenever
she is a זבה, Zava, she is a זבה. Zava. There are
many attested cases, there's a lot in the medical literature about this
actually, that even girls soon after they're born often can have some
kind of vaginal discharge that could be considered something along the lines
of נדה Niddah or something like that. So there is, there's real
physical and medical reasons why חז"ל Chazal were talking about this even
for prepubescent girls. It's going to come up when we learn מסכת
נדה Masechet Niddah for sure. Okay. מסתמיך ואזיל רבי יהודה נשיאה אכתפיה
דרבי שמלאי. mistamich ve-azil Rabbi Yehuda Nesia a-katfei de-Rabbi Simlai.
So now we're going to get back into our discussion of the
oil. Okay. So wait a second. Our משנה Mishna had said that
the oil had been prohibited by
בית שמאי ובית הלל Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel and then had been
permitted by רבי, Rebbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi the author
of the משנה. Mishna. Who is רבי יהודה נשיאה? Rabbi Yehuda Nesia?
Grandson of רבי. Rebbi,
Seemingly רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehuda Nesia is the grandson of רבי.
Rebbi. This story doesn't make any sense, I think. It certainly makes
less sense if the character in the story is the grandson of
the person who made the oil permissible and not the person who
made the oil permissible. Maybe רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, the
grandson, actually sat on his grandfather's בית דין. Beit Din. He was
even, you know, a precocious young man. Perhaps, you know, he grew
up in רבי's Rebbi. household, maybe he had reached enough level of
תורה Torah scholarship to be on the court at the time when
רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, was the נשיא. Nasi. So it
at least raises some questions why he's sort of talking in the
first person about about things that his grandfather was responsible for. But
let's see. Okay. So
מסתמיך ואזיל רבי יהודה נשיאה אכתפיה דרבי שמלאי. mistamich ve-azil Rabbi Yehuda
Nesia a-katfei de-Rabbi Simlai. Rabbi Yehuda Nesia was traveling, he was leaning
on the shoulder of Rabbi Simlai שמעיה, shmaya, who was his servant
or his attendant. It's very interesting that part of the כבוד kavod
they gave to the נשיא Nasi is that they would have an
attendant who in this case actually the servant, the attendant, is Rabbi
Simlai, one of the great of the later תנאים Tannaim or early
אמוראים Amoraim who we are aware of. So it's very interesting that
he was serving him and he was actually senior senior to him
as well. So אמר ליה שמלאי, amar lei Simlai, he says to
him, hey Simlai, לאו היית אמש בבית המדרש כשהתרנו את השמן. lav
hayita emesh be-veit hamidrash keshe-hitarnu et ha-shemen. You weren't in the בית
מדרש Beit Midrash yesterday. Yesterday? You weren't in the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash yesterday when we permitted the oil. So it's interesting to say
yesterday. It might mean in the past previously or something. It's sort
of a strange, like I said, some of the details in the
story don't exactly line up. אמר לו בימינו תתיר אף את הפת.
amar lo beyameinu tatir af et ha-pat. So he said back to
him, in our day תתיר אף את הפת, tatir af et ha-pat,
you are probably going to permit even bread. That is, what happened,
that your grandson permitted the oil and we already know also that
רבי Rebbi's had some issue with the bread as well, under which
circumstances does the גזירה gezera against פת עכו"ם pat akum apply or
not and all sorts of things, right, all those details we dealt
with a few days ago.
So he says, in your day, in your day you're going to
permit the bread as well. אמר לו אם כן קרו לן בי
דינא שריא. amar lo im ken karu lan bei dina sharya. He
said back to him,
if so, they're going to call my court, that is it sounds
like he's comparing himself to his grandfather, he's saying my grandfather's court
permitted the oil, if I'll permit bread they'll call me a permissive
בית דין, Beit Din, which seemingly is a bad thing. דתנן, de-tnan,
based on the precedent that was set hundreds of years in the
past, which is from מסכת עדיות, Masechet Eduyot, העיד רבי יוסי בן
יועזר איש צרידה. he'id Rabbi Yose ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah. Rabbi Yose
ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah, maybe he's not רבי Rebbi Yose ben Yoezer
actually, he's just יוסי בן יועזר, Yose ben Yoezer, the man from
צרידה. Tzeredah. על איל קמצא דכן. al ayal kamtza dachkan. He testified
that this kind of locust is a kosher kind of locust, sorry,
על איל
קמצא דכן al ayal kamtza dachkan that it's, that it's kosher, that
it's טהור. tahor. ועל משקה בית מטבחיא דכיין, ve-al mashke beit matbechaya
dachyan, and that the liquid from the slaughterhouse in the Temple is
pure. We're going to see what that means as well on עמוד
ב'. amud bet. ועל דיקרב למיתה מסאב, ve-al di-kerav le-mita mesa'av, and
that someone who is close to death, or,
or that one who touches a dead body or something like that
מסאב, mesa'av, will transfer impurity, is מיטמא. metamei. דקרו ליה יוסף שריא.
de-karu leh Yosef sharya. They called him not יוסי בן יועזר איש
צרידה, Yose ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah, they also... also called him יוסף
שריא Yosef Sharya because he was so permissive, because he had these
lenient rulings. So we're going to see the third one doesn't seem
permissive at all and it's going to be discussed in the גמרא,
Gemara, and the first two also, like, what are these have to
do with anything? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, התם שרא תלת. Hatam
shara tlat. No, the reason why is because he permitted three things.
ומר שרא חדא U'mar shara chada and I only did one thing,
right, I would even if I would permit the bread I would
only be permitting one thing, or I permitted the oil. ואי שרי
מר חדא אחריתא, Ve'ee shari mar chada achrita, and if I would
permit something else, הוו להו תרתין. Havvu lehu tartin. So then I'll
only have two
דהוין. dehavvin. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, אנא שראי אחריתא. Ana sharai
achrita. So no because it's I already, I רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi
Yehuda Nesi'ah talking about himself, he says I already have one other
permissive position that I didn't even tell you about. So מאי היא?
Mai hi? What is it? דתנן, Detnan, it's based on this משנה.
Mishna. זה גיטך, Ze gittech, if a man says to his wife
this is your גט, get, אם לא באתי מכאן ועד שנים עשר
חודש, im lo bati mikan ve'ad shneim asar chodesh, if I don't
return from this long trip from now within the next twelve months.
That is, he's going away on a trip, he gives her the
גט get now on the condition that if he does not return
from the trip the גט get seemingly the גט get should take
effect now at the time he left on the trip. Okay, ומת
בתוך שנים עשר חודש, U'meit betoch shneim asar chodesh, and he died
during the twelve months, אינו גט, eino get, it's not a kosher
גט get because we say the principle אין גט לאחר מיתה. ein
get le'achar mita. You can't give a retroactive גט get after you've
died because then you sort of could undermine the whole institution of
יבום Yibbum and there would be a problem there and also just
how does it retroactively take hold? A dead person has no legal
standing to give over the גט. get. Okay, ותני עלה, Vetani ala,
and then he taught about that later, that is in the period
of the early אמוראים, Amoraim, they taught about that משנה, Mishna, seemingly
רבי יהודה נשיאה's Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah position, ורבותינו התירוה להינשא. Verabboseinu hitiruha
lehinnasei. Our rabbis permitted her to marry. ואמרינן, Ve'amrinan, מן רבותינו? man
Rabboseinu? Who is רבותינו? Rabboseinu? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in בבל Bavel quoting שמואל
Shmuel said בי דינא דשרו משחא. Be dina desharu mshacha. It's the
same בית דין Beis Din that permitted the oil. So it also
sounds like the oil was permitted in the time of רבי יהודה
נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, not רבי. Rabbi Again, it's a little bit
strange. Okay, so but the point is so they allowed her to
marry, that is even though we said אינו גט, eino get, they
made some kind of תקנה takkanah to actually there's some similar case
where the גט get is good. חנניה Chananya you have a question?
If he died then why can't she...
because the point will be that if he died then she'll have
a זיקה zika to his brother to do יבום Yibbum and that
then she'll so to save her from having to deal with יבום
Yibbum the man would want to give her the גט get in
advance. Right. Or because even if it's some kind of a concern
that there's a...
yeah I think that's the main concern usually with giving these kind
of גיטין. gittin.
So they overrode the idea that it...
it seems, we're going to get to it, there's a retroactive גט
get under... right, what they changed or what they overruled was some
kind of principle about how the retroactive גט get takes effect. When,
when would it take effect to save you from the problem of
אין גט לאחר מיתה ein get le'achar mita but to still make
it so the גט get was a kosher גט. get.
Yes, very good. But also he's originally saying if I don't come
back after twelve months, which is more, right, then we might not
know that he died.
Right, it's whether or not, right, so we don't know whether he
died, here we know for sure that he died. Anyway, סברי לה
כרבי יוסי. Savri lah ke'Rabbi Yosei. It seems like this position was
based on the opinion of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, דאמר זמנו של
שטר מוכיח עליו, de'amar zmano shel shtar mochiach alav, because the time
written in the שטר, shtar, the time, the date written on the
גט get is a testament to when the גט get takes effect.
And therefore it sounds like our presumption is that if he gives
her the גט get today and it says on it sixth of
אדר תשע"ח, Adar Tash'ach, that that means that once if he doesn't
come back twelve months from now the גט get will take effect
from right now. And therefore if he dies in the middle then
it will be a גט לאחר מיתה get le'achar mita because the
גט get was given beforehand but the תנאי tnai is fulfilled afterwards.
So that's part of the... sorry that it won't be a גט
לאחר מיתה get le'achar mita because the גט get will actually have
taken effect earlier only that the condition was fulfilled later. Okay, retroactive
conditions are kind of tricky, you have to keep it in your
head a little bit,
okay. מוכיח עליו. Mochiach alav. ואמר רבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא בר
אבא, Ve'amar Rabbi Abba breih de'Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, so רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba quoted
his father רבי חייא בר אבא, Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, דרבי יהודה
הנשיא הורה ולא הודו לו. de'Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi horah velo hodu lo.
רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi the grandfather of רבי יהודה נשיאה,
Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, tried to permit it and the other rabbis did
not agree to him. כל שעתו, Kol sha'ato, his entire lifetime they
never agreed to him.
ואמרי לה כל סייעתו. Ve'amri lah kol sayato. And some say that
not כל שעתו kol sha'ato his whole life but כל סייעתו kol
sayato all of his supporters. That is, no one agreed to him
in his lifetime or during his tenure, but when his grandson took
over then they were able to institute this new more permissive opinion
based on the opinion of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei that actually the
retroactive condition will be fulfilled,
considered from the time the גט get was given and therefore won't
be a גט לאחר מיתה get le'achar mita and therefore the woman
would be able to remarry. אמר ליה
רבי אלעזר לההוא סבא.
Amar lei Rabbi
Elazar lehahu saba. I think it's should be רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
right, the אמורא Amora רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, yeah. אמר ליה רבי
אלעזר לההוא סבא, Amar lei Rabbi Elazar lehahu saba, רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar said to this older man, כי שריתוה לאלתר שריתוה, ki sharituha
le'altar sharituha, when they permitted it they permitted it immediately.
or
not only if he would die, but meaning that he didn't come,
meaning so is it, right, oh that he died, right, that since
he died now do we have to wait until the end of
the 12 months or not?
And that was part of the original תנאי.
tnai. ותיבעי לך, V’tiba'ei lach, מתניתין דתנן. matnitin d’tnan. So this the
question is answered by this mishna. The mishna says: הרי זה גיטך
מעכשיו אם לא באתי מכאן עד שנים עשר חודש. Harei zeh gittech
me'achshav im lo bati mikan ad shneim asar chodesh. This is your
get now if I don't arrive between now and the next 12
months.
ומת בתוך שנים עשר חודש, U-met betoch shneim asar chodesh, הוי גט.
havi get. That's a good get. דהא איקיים ליה תנאיה. De-ha ikayim
lei tna'ei. Because he fulfilled the תנאי, tnai, because there's no way
he can come visit her within the 12 months.
ותיבעי לך לאלתר הוי גיטא? V’tiba'ei lach l'alter havi gitta? Because at
the time that he gave the get, that it was a kosher
get, דהא לא אתא, de-ha lo ata, because he had not, he
can't arrive, he didn't arrive? או דילמא לאחר שנים עשר חודש דהא
איקיים ליה תנאיה? O dilma l'achar shneim asar chodesh de-ha kayim lei
tna'ei? Or do you have to wait until 12 months because that's
when the condition will actually be fulfilled? So אין הכי נמי. In
hachi nami. So I agree with you that it's parallel to that
question in the mishna, אלא משום דהוה בההוא מניינא. ela mishum de-hava
behahu minyana.
But because that was
not addressed in that when they took a vote on that issue.
Okay. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Abaye said: הכל מודים לכשתצא חמה מנרתיקה.
Hakol modim l'chsheteitzei chamah minartikei.
So Abaye says everyone says that if the תנאי tnai that the
husband makes about the get is when the sun comes out of
its pouch, out of its wallet, because the sun at night goes
inside of a bag to keep the light inside so it gets
dark, because it goes on the top side of the רקיע. rakia.
Okay. לכי נפקא, L’chi nafka,
so when it comes out, כאמר לה. ka’amar lah. That he meant
when the sun comes out. וכי מית בליליא, Ve-chi meit beleilaya, and
if he died at night? So what happened? The man gives his
wife a get in the afternoon and he says on the condition
when the sun comes out of its bag, that is when the
sun rises tomorrow, the get should take effect. So wait a second.
So what if he died in the middle of the night? That's
a similar kind of case. That is, he died before the condition
was fulfilled. Okay, so כי מית בליליא גט לאחר מיתה הוא. ki
meit beleilaya get l’achar mita hu. That's a גט לאחר מיתה. get
l'achar mita. The get is trying to take effect after he's died
because he said לכי נפקא, l’chi nafka, when it comes out. But
if he said על מנת שתצא חמה מנרתיקה, al m’nat sheteitzei chamah
minartikei,
if he said it's on the condition that the sun comes out
of its bag, מעכשיו כאמר לה. me’achshav ka’amar lah. Then על מנת
al m’nat is when you say על מנת al m’nat on the
condition that, that's a way of making a conditional get where the
condition means the get should take effect now based on a later
condition. But if you say לכי נפקא l’chi nafka when it comes
out, you're saying I make the get dependent on the תנאי tnai
being fulfilled in the future. So these have very different applicability exactly
for the question of גט לאחר מיתה. get l’achar mita. Because if
you give a גט לאחר מיתה, get l’achar mita, then because you're
trying to make the get only take effect after the condition is
fulfilled, so if you've died before the condition is fulfilled then it's
a גט לאחר מיתה get l’achar mita and then she'll have to
do ייבום yibum and it's not a good get. But if you
say על מנת, al m’nat, then you're saying I want the get
to be good from now on the condition that this later thing
happens and that will retroactively make the get a kosher get. So
these are two slightly different kinds of retroactive conditions. Okay. וכי מית
בליליא הא הוה ליה תנאה. Ve-chi meit beleilaya ha hava lei tna'ei.
But if he died at night, you still fulfilled the תנאי. tnai.
הוי גט מחיים. Havi get m'chayim.
So and if you say it's על מנת, al m’nat, then you're
saying that the get is a גט מחיים. get m'chayim. It's a
get while he was still alive because he gave the get the
day before while he was alive.
הוא כדירב הונא. Hu kidei Rav Huna. And this is like the
opinion of רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא, De-amar Rav Huna,
כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו דמי. kol ha-omer al m’nat ke-omer
me’achshav dami. רב הונא Rav Huna said a general rule: whenever you
say על מנת al m’nat on the condition of, you're really saying
that you want the get or this transaction or whatever it is
to take effect now
dependent on a later condition, rather than making the effect of the
get or the effect of the transaction or whatever dependent on the
condition as well. So it's a retroactive condition, not a delayed effect.
Okay. לא נחלקו אלא באם. Lo nechelku ela be-im. Yeah.
Wouldn't it be the case
where the רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi and his court disagree,
yes, does his opinion still does
his opinion considered valid even if the court disagrees?
No, his opinion was only made valid two generations later when his
grandson actually enacted it.
Okay, so the court can overrule?
Of course. The נשיא Nasi is only one, he is first among
equals to borrow the term, meaning the נשיא Nasi of the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin is a voting member. He has a vote but he only
has one vote.
So even though he's in charge, he's more seniority, more authority, whatever
that usually would mean also that he has to speak last, right?
Because we go going up in seniority.
So this also applied to like when we were speaking about the
prophets yesterday and their court. The court would still have that power
over legislative matters for sure. Of course, if it's a court, it's
a court, you have to vote, yeah.
And does this still kind of prove that this court was lenient
or something?
No, so what we're doing so far right now, we're just explaining
what was רבי יהודה הנשיא's Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi leniency and we went
on a tangent about גט לאחר מיתה. Get L'achar Mitah. The point
was that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi enacted a more lenient
position based on רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi position and his grandfather's position
about a גט. get. So if he would permit the bread, then
he would already have ended up permitting three things because he was
on the court that did the oil, and he has this thing
about גט לאחר מיתה, Get L'achar Mitah, and he would have the
bread case. And then they'll call him בית דין שריא, Beit Din
Sharya, a permissive בית דין, beit din, and he doesn't want to
be called that. I have a story about that after.
We're still part of the tangent about גט לאחר מיתה Get L'achar
Mitah and then we're going to come back to עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah soon, don't worry. But as something I heard, I forget who
I heard this from, was that you know if you want to
learn a topic, right, you can't just learn הלכות גיטין Hilchot Gittin
by learning מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin. There are all sorts of סוגיות
sugyot all across ש"ס Shas that have relevance to all different kinds
of topics. You have to know where to look. Okay.
לא נחלקו אלא באם. Lo necheleku ela be'im. There was a disagreement.
So there's no disagreement about על מנת al menat and there's no
disagreement about כי, ki, but there is a disagreement about אם. im.
אם, im, if the sun comes out, is if like כי, ki,
when it happens, that is you're saying I make the effect also
conditional, that is the גט get will only take effect at the
time that the condition is fulfilled, or is it more like על
מנת al menat and you want the גט get to take effect
now dependent on a later condition being fulfilled? So that's the question.
So, sorry, באם תצא. be'im tetze. If, if the sun comes out.
רבי יהודה הנשיא סבר לה כרבי יוסי. Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi savar la
ke'Rabbi Yossi. רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi holds the position like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi דאמר זמנו של שטר מוכיח עליו. de'amar zmano
shel shtar mochiach alav. He says that the date written in the
שטר shtar is indicative of when you intend the שטר shtar to
take effect והוה ליה כמהיום. ve'hava lei k'me'hayom. It's like from right
now, from today. אם מתי כמעכשיו, im meti k'me'achshav,
it's like from right now if I die. Sorry, כמהיום אם מתי,
k'me'hayom im meti, it's like from today if I die, כמעכשיו אם
מתי k'me'achshav im meti or it's like from right now if I
die. ורבנן לית להו דרבי יוסי. Ve'rabbanan leit lehu de'Rabbi Yossi. And
the other rabbis disagreed with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi והוה ליה כזה
גיטיך אם מתי. ve'hava lei k'zeh giteich im meti. He said it's
like this is your get if I die גרידא gerada without any
condition that the גט get should be כשר kosher from now on
the time that it comes into effect later. So this was the
whole tangent about רבי יהודה הנשיא's Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi thing. Why did
רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, not want to be a בית
דין שריא? Beit Din Sharya? The question, I forget who asked the
question, the question was asked to רבי יוסף חיים זוננפלד, Rabbi Yosef
Chaim Sonnenfeld, who was one of the leaders of the חרדי Charedi
community in Jerusalem early 20th century. Someone asked him wait a second,
רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi don't we, it's a good thing
to be permissive, don't we say כוח דהיתירא עדיף ליה? koach de'hetera
adifa lei? It's actually it indicates better confidence in your position if
you're able to be lenient. It's something to strive for, to try
to find leniencies as much as possible. And so Rav Sonnenfeld said,
no, no, no, yeah כוח דהיתירא עדיף ליה, koach de'hetera adifa lei,
but there's some lines you don't cross. That is you still have
to have a certain threshold of what you think is permissible and
what you think isn't. We don't try to find the lenient position
in every single case. So this was part of רבי Rebbi. יהודה
הנשיא's Yehuda HaNasi, hesitancy is that even though there's a value in
trying to be lenient at times or in certain cases, but not
to develop a reputation of always being lenient, because then people won't
take you seriously or won't trust your opinions when you have to
be strict, or something like that. Okay. גופא. Gufa.
Maybe there's just some topics that aren't worth taking the risk for?
Yeah, for sure. Right, some things it's really important, right here, we're
talking about היתר עגונה. heter aguna. This is an important situation where
this woman is going to be trapped with a יבם, yavam, the
יבם yavam is overseas or the יבם yavam is mentally incapable or
something, who knows, and she's going to have to marry someone she
doesn't want. So we're trying to find a way for her to
be able to get a גט get that's a good גט. get.
Okay. גופא. Gufa. So we're going back to the discussion of יוסי
בן יועזר, Yossi ben Yoezer, the three cases that יוסי בן יועזר
Yossi ben Yoezer was permissive about. Okay. העיד יוסי בן יועזר איש
צרידה. He'id Yossi ben Yoezer ish Tzreida. So יוסי בן... I like
him because the yeshiva I went to in Israel is on יוסי
בן יועזר Yose ben Yoezer street, so it has a soft spot
in my heart. יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה על איל קמצא דכן
Yossi ben Yoezer ish Tzreida al ayal kamtza dachan that the איל
קמצא ayal kamtza locust is a pure locust, a kosher
locust ועל משקה בית מטבחיא דכן ve'al mashke beit mitbachaya dachan and
that the liquid in the slaughterhouse in the temple is not טמא,
tamei, is טהור tahor liquids ועל די קרב למיתא מסתאב ve'al di-krav
le-meita mesta'av and that someone who comes close to a corpse becomes
טמא. tamei. וקרו ליה יוסף שריא. Vekaru lei Yosef Sharya. They called
him permissive Yosef. So מאי
איל קמצא? mai ayal kamtza? What is איל קמצא, ayal kamtza, what
is this kind of locust? רב פפא אמר שושיבא. Rav Papa Amar
Shushiva. Rav Papa said it's the שושיבא shushiva ורב חייא בר. ve'Rav
Chiya bar. עמי משמיה דעולא אמר סוסביל Ami mishmei de'Ulla amar Susbil
and you know I don't know the anatomy of all different kinds
of grasshoppers and locusts and things to know which species they're talking
about. They obviously had they knew. There are some communities that still
claim that they have a מסורה mesora of which kinds of grasshoppers
and locusts and things are kosher, and many communities have lost that
מסורה, mesora, which is a very bad thing. רב פפא אמר שושיבא.
Rav Pappa amar Shushiva.
He suggested it's the elongated...
the elongated head. Okay. Right. רש״י Rashi says in four words: מין
חגב וראשו ארוך. min chagav verosho aruch. It's some kind of a
locust with a long head. I don't know. רש״י Rashi probably didn't
know what kind of locust it was either.
But how does he know to give that explanation?
That's a good question too. That's another topic for another time. Right,
there's a lot been written about where did רש״י Rashi get it
from? Anyway, okay. רב פפא אמר שושיבא וקמיפלגי בראשו ארוך. Rav Pappa
amar Shushiva vekamipalgi berosho aruch. Their debate is about the long head.
מר סבר ראשו ארוך אסור. Mar savar rosho aruch assur. One says
that the one with a long head is a prohibited kind of
locust. ומר סבר ראשו ארוך מותר Umar savar rosho aruch muttar and
one says ones with long heads are actually permissible. ורב חייא בר
אמי משמיה דעולא אמר סוסביל veRav Chiyya bar Ami mishmei de'Ulla amar
Susbil
and רב חייא בר אמי Rav Chiyya bar Ami quoted עולא Ulla
saying a סוסביל. Susbil. What is a סוסביל? Susbil? רש״י Rashi says
אין ראשו ארוך. ein rosho aruch. It's not a long head, אבל
אין כנפיו חופין את רובו, aval ein knafav chofin et rubo,
the wings are not big enough to cover the majority of the
body. לראות לעינים, lirot le'einayim,
but in a way that's visible to the eyes, only they only
cover the majority בצמצום, betzimtzum, exactly
the majority of the body. Because the הלכה halacha for a kosher
locust, the wings have to be big enough to cover majority of
the body. It's discussed in many different contexts. What kind of a
רוב rov do we need? Do we need רוב rov that's a
majority, that's a visible majority, or do we need a רוב rov
that's just... just a רוב? rov? It could be 50.000001% and that's
enough of a majority or does it have to be visible, it
has to be 55% or something like that. So that's the question.
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסור. kulei alma lo pligi de'assur. So they
say that everyone agrees that if the head is long, no one
disagrees that that one is prohibited. That's a טרפה treif locust. והכא
בכנפיו חופין את רובו על ידי הדחק, vehacha bichnafav chofin et rubo
al yedei hadachak, that the wings only just barely cover the body.
קמיפלגי. kamipalgi. That's the debate. מר סבר רובא כל דהוא. Mar savar
rova kol dehu. Some says that you only need an exact, just
barely a majority, 50.0001%. דהוא בעינא. dehu ba'ina. ומר סבר רובא דמינכר
בעינא. umar savar rova deminchar ba'ina.
One says we need actually a visible majority. Okay, let's continue. על
משקה בי מטבחיא דכיין. al mashke bei mitbachaya dachyan. That the liquid
from the slaughterhouse is considered טהור. tahor. This is mostly discussed in
פסחים Pesachim in the second chapter in the big long סוגיא sugya
about טומאה וטהרה tumah vetahara there. עיין שם. ayen sham. So מאי
דכיין? mai dachyan? What does it mean that it's טהור, tahor, right?
I love also that they're using the Aramaic word דכיא, dachya, right,
דכיין, dachyan, rather than the Hebrew. It's just interesting, you don't see
that regularly in the תלמוד. Talmud. So מאי דכיין? mai dachyan? רב
אמר דכיין ממש. Rav amar dachyan mamash. רב Rav says that actually
the liquids are not considered liquids enough to be to be considered
impure, or they're special liquids that for some reason do not fall
under the normal laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetahara for liquids. ושמואל
אמר דכיין מלטמא אחרים. uShmuel amar dachyan miletamei acherim. שמואל Shmuel says
it only means that they're pure enough that they don't have the
power to make other things impure. אבל טומאת עצמן יש בהם. aval
tumat atzman yesh bahem. But they could become impure themselves, they just
couldn't transfer it to something else. This has obviously a big question
for if you would touch those liquids directly. Well, not if you
touch the liquids directly, because they can't make you טמא, tamei, but
if you want to drink them or if you want...
even there, right? I'm trying to think of what's the actual נפקא
מינה nafka mina between these cases. I have to think a bit
more about it.
דכיין dachyan means טהור tahor like, right, רמז למרדכי מן התורה מנין,
remez leMordechai min haTorah minayin, right, in the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha
the מור דרור, mor deror, the pure myrrh is מרא דכיא. mara
dachya. So טהור tahor or זך, zach, right, דכיא dachya is like
זך. zach. It's like... it's like pure, right? But it means pure
both in a pure sense and also pure in a טהור tahor
sense, right? טהור Tahor is also used that way where we say
זהב טהור. zahav tahor. זהב טהור Zahav tahor is like saying it's
זך. zach. It's like it's been purified, it's been... the other metals
have been removed from the alloy. Okay. רב אמר דכיין ממש. Rav
amar dachyan mamash. So רב Rav says that it actually is really
pure. קסבר טומאת משקין דרבנן. kasavar tumat mashkin derabbanan. That רב Rav
thinks that the entire institution that liquids, the seven liquids, could become
טמא tamei is a דין דרבנן. din derabbanan. It's only a rabbinic
law. וכי גזרו רבנן טומאה במשקים דעלמא. vechi gazru rabbanan tumah bemashkim
de'alma. When the rabbis made the law regarding טומאה tumah for liquids,
they only said it for normal liquids, משקים דעלמא, mashkim de'alma, liquids
out in the world. אבל במשקה בי מטבחיא, aval bemashke bei mitbachaya,
but they didn't make the law regarding the liquids of the slaughterhouse,
בי מטבחיא לא גזרו רבנן. bei mitbachaya lo gazru rabbanan. The rabbis
did not make a rabbinic טומאה. tumah. ושמואל אמר דכיין מלטמא אחרים.
uShmuel amar dachyan miletamei acherim. שמואל Shmuel says that it means that
they're pure from being able to transfer טומאה tumah to other things.
אבל טומאת עצמן יש בהם. aval tumat atzman yesh bahem. But they
could become טמא tamei themselves. קסבר טומאת משקין דאורייתא. kasavar tumat mashkin
de'oraita. שמואל Shmuel thinks טומאת משקין, tumat mashkin, the that liquids could
become טמא tamei is actually a דין דאורייתא. din de'oraita. לטמא אחרים
דרבנן. letamei acherim derabbanan. But their ability to convey impurity to other
substances or other people or other things is only דרבנן. derabbanan. So
they both agree that the Rabbinic law, whatever Rabbinic law was instituted
only applies outside the Temple and not inside the Temple, and the
question is what was the דאורייתא d'Oraita *de'oraita* and what was the
דרבנן de-rabanan *derabanan*. According to רב *Rav*, nothing about טומאת משקין *tumat
mashkin* is דאורייתא d'Oraita *de'oraita*. According to שמואל *Shmuel*, the fact that
liquids could become טמא tamei. *tamei* is דאורייתא d'Oraita? *de'oraita*, but that
they could be מטמא *metamei*, they could make other things impure, is
only a דרבנן *derabanan*. Very interesting. Normally you wouldn't think there should
be a distinction between being able to become טמא tamei *tamei* and
being able to make something else טמא tamei *tamei*. But here we
see a distinction between them. This gets back to יוסי בן יועזר
Yose ben Yoezer *Yosei ben Yoezer*. This goes back to clarifying what
did יוסי בן יועזר Yose ben Yoezer *Yosei ben Yoezer* because יוסי
בן יועזר Yose ben Yoezer *Yosei ben Yoezer*
said, משקין דבית מטבחיא דכן *mashkin debeit mitbachaya dachan*.
The liquids of the slaughterhouse are טהור tahor. *tahor* and the question
is, and that was a leniency. It was a leniency and the
question is what did he mean by that?
Did he mean that
they cannot make other things impure or did he mean they themselves
cannot become impure? And that's מחלוקת *machloket* between רב *Rav* and שמואל
*Shmuel* 400 years after him. Either way it was a leniency. Either
way it was a leniency, right. The question is just clarifying what
his position was. ועל דיקרב למיתא מסאב *ve'al dikrav lemita mesa'av* and
that if you come in contact or touch a corpse you become
טמא tamei, *tamei* וקרו ליה יוסף שריא *vekaro lei Yosef Sharya*. They
called him the permissive Yosef. So יוסף אסרא מבעי ליה *Yosef assara
mibayei lei*. It should call him the one who prohibits because this
sounds like a prohibitive ruling, not a permissive ruling.
Yeah. Well, what I was going to say, there's places in the
תורה *Torah* where it's pretty
clear that a liquid can transmit טומאה tumah *tuma*. No, not necessarily.
It's clear in the תורה *Torah* that if a liquid lands on
a food or is poured on a food that then someone טמא
tamei *tamei* who touches the food, the food will become טמא tamei.
*tamei*. That's מכשירין *machshirim*. מכשירין *machshirim* is a different principle than טומאת
משקין *tumat mashkin*. מכשירין *machshirim* means if foods get wet with these
seven liquids, then the food becomes susceptible to becoming טמא tamei *tamei*.
טומאת משקין *tumat mashkin* means the liquid itself could become טמא tamei
*tamei*. Those are different principles. There is a verse in ויקרא *Vayikra*,
וכי ירק
הזב על הטהור *vechi yarak hazav al hatahor*. Oh, but that's different.
That's רוקו של זב *ruko shel zav*. רוקו של זב *ruko shel
zav* means the liquids, bodily excretions of a person who is a
זב *zav*, their bodily emissions are considered to be... it's not about
משקין *mashkin*. No, but they're not among the seven משקין *mashkin* that
become טמא tamei *tamei*. The seven משקין *mashkin* specifically... now I forget
the mnemonic, but I know the seven: water, dew, blood, honey, milk,
wine, and olive oil. So those seven liquids—why dew and water are
separate things, whatever—but seven liquids are both for טומאת משקין *tumat mashkin*,
that they themselves could become טמא tamei, *tamei* if someone טמא tamei.
*tamei* touches them, or that they could be מכשירין *machshirim* if they
land on a food or poured on a food and then the
food is touched by a person who is טמא tamei. *tamei*, the
food becomes טמא tamei, *tamei*. But those seven liquids... so not about
רוקו של זב *ruko shel zav*, spit or urine or semen from
a זב *zav*, or a דם נידה *dam nida* or something like
that. That's bodily emissions from someone who themselves are a source of
טומאה tumah *tuma*. So their bodily fluids are considered to be טמא
tamei. *tamei* and מטמא *metamei*, not because it's a law of the
liquid but because it's part of their body. So it's a distinction.
Certainly there are what we would call liquids, but in the halakhic
sense, משקין *mashkin* refers to those seven liquids and those two different
הלכות *halachot*, מכשירין *machshirim* which is certainly a דאורייתא de-oraita *de'oraita* and
the question of טומאת משקין *tumat mashkin* which is the debate between
רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* we just learned. Okay. So why isn't
he יוסף אסרא מבעי ליה *Yosef assara mibayei lei*? ועוד *ve'od*, further,
דאורייתא היא *de'oraita hi*. Wait a second, touching a dead body is
מטמא *metamei*, of course touching a dead body is טמא *tamei*, that's
a פסוק passuk *pasuk*. The פסוק *pasuk* says וכל אשר יגע על
פני השדה בחלל חרב או במת *vechol asher yiga al penei hasadeh
bechalal cherev o vemet*. If you touch a corpse, you touch someone
who was killed in war, whatever, or a dead body, you become
טמא *tamei*. We go over. So דאורייתא *de'oraita* דיקרב טמא *dikrav tamei*.
So the דאורייתא *de'oraita* principle is that if you touch the body,
you are טמא *tamei*. דיקרב בדיקרב טהור tahor *dikrav bedikrav tahor*. But
if you touch something that touched the body, you would be טהור
*tahor*. That is, like something, one stage removed. Okay. ואתו אינהו וגזרו
אפילו דיקרב בדיקרב *va'atu inhu vegazru afilu dikrav bedikrav*. So the Rabbis
came in later and said that a two steps removed, you touch
something which is touching a dead body, then you are also טמא
*tamei* for that. ואתא איהו ve'ata ihu ואוקמה אדאורייתא *ve'ata ihu ve'ukma
ade'oraita*. And then later he came and said that you should uphold
the law like the דאורייתא *de'oraita* law. דיקרב בדיקרב נמי *dikrav bedikrav
nami*. So that is, no, we should say he's יוסף שריא *Yosef
Sharya* because actually what he's saying is only keep the דאורייתא *de'oraita*.
When he said, right, על דיקרב למיתא מסאב *al dikrav lemita mesa'av*,
if you touch a dead body you're טמא *tamei*, he's saying don't
follow this even more strict Rabbinic rule that if you touch one
stage removed that you'll be טמא *tamei*. Okay. Whatever a person who
is טמא touches also becomes טמא. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבא משמיה דמר
זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן, amaru rabanan kamei d'Rava mishmei d'Mar Zutra brei
d'Rav Nachman, so the rabbis were quoting in front of רבא Rava
quoting from מר זוטרא Mar Zutra the son of רב נחמן Rav
Nachman דאמר משמיה דרב נחמן d'amar mishmei d'Rav Nachman quoting רב נחמן
Rav Nachman דאורייתא דקרב בדקרב בחיבורין טומאת שבעה. d'Oraita d'krav b'd'krav b'chiburin
tumat shiva. So if you're touching, the דאורייתא principle is if you
touch something which is touching the dead body directly. בחיבורין, b'chiburin, they
are actually attached, so that's טומאת שבעה. tumat shiva. That's a seven-day
impurity like the טומאה tumah that comes from touching the corpse directly.
שלא בחיבורין, shelo b'chiburin, but if they're not actually currently attached, then
טומאת ערב, tumat erev, it's only a one-day טומאה tumah, that you
go to the מקוה mikvah and it's removed overnight. ואתו אינהו וגזרו
אפילו שלא בחיבורין טומאת שבעה, v'atu inhu v'gazru afilu shelo b'chiburin tumat
shiva, and then the rabbis said, ah, let's actually extend the one-day
טומאה tumah from the Torah into seven-days טומאה, tumah. ואתא איהו ואוקמיה
אדאורייתא. v'ata ihu v'ukmye ad'Oraita. And then יוסי בן יועזר Yose ben
Yoezer came and said no no no, let's not follow this stringency
to keep seven-days טומאה tumah for touching something which touched a dead
body, we'll keep it back to the דאורייתא rule, only keep for
one-day טומאה. tumah דאורייתא מאי? d'Oraita mai? And what's the דאורייתא? דכתיב,
dichtiv, הנוגע במת לכל נפש אדם וטמא שבעת ימים. hanogea b'met l'chol
nefesh adam v'tamei shivat yamim. If you touch a corpse, then you
become טמא for seven days. וכתיב, uchitiv, וכל אשר יגע בו הטמא
יטמא, v'chol asher yiga bo hatamei yitma, and the פסוק says whomever
touches something that touched by someone טמא becomes טמא, וכתיב, uchitiv, הנפש
הנגעת תטמא עד הערב. hanefesh hanogaat titema ad haerev. So it sounds
like and if you touch something which touched a corpse, then you
only are טמא for one day. הכיצד? hakeitzad? What are we talking
about? כאן בחיבורין כאן שלא בחיבורין, kan b'chiburin kan shelo b'chiburin, and
the distinction is whether it was still attached. That is, the clothing
of a corpse or a, right, you touch, you touch a shirt
that is being worn by a dead body, the תכריכים tachrichim of
a מת met or something like that. So that's חיבורין, chiburin, that's
still attached, so that's considered to be sort of an extension of
the body, so the טומאה tumah is for seven days. But if
you go, you, you, they take the shirt off and they put
it in a pile and you touch it, then you're טמא. The
shirt is אב הטומאה av hatumah of something which became טמא from
a corpse, so you become טמא for one day because it's no
longer directly connected to the body. Like before the father wanted to
get the knife out of. Something like the father wanted to get
the knife out of, so it wouldn't be חיבור. chibur. Not only
it wouldn't be חיבור, chibur, he wanted to take it out before
he died so it won't be טמא at all. Okay. אמר להו
רבא. amar lehu Rava. So רבא Rava said back to them, לאו
אמינא לכו לא תתלו בי בוקי סריקי. lav amina l'chu lo titlu
bi buki sariki. So רבא Rava said back to them, like you
guys, you're making mistakes, you're like רש"י Rashi says, כדים ריקים, kadim
reikim, you're like empty jars. You don't know what you're talking about.
But wait a second, אלא רב נחמן הכי אמר רב נחמן. ela
Rav Nachman hachi amar Rav Nachman. And רבא Rava said no no
no, this is what רב נחמן Rav Nachman said. ספק טומאה ברשות
הרבים התיר להם. safek tumah birshut harabim hitir lahem. That יוסי בן
יועזר instituted the rule that in a doubtful case of טומאה tumah.
that takes place in in public, let's say, רשות הרבים reshut harabim
here refers to a place where there are three people have joined
together, at least, minimum we learned in מסכת סוטה masechet Sotah as
well and מסכת נזיר masechet Nazir if you remember back several years
now. ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים התיר להם. safek tumah birshut harabim hitir
lahem. So יוסי בן יועזר repealed a stringency that had applied, right?
Until this point, the rule had been every ספק דאורייתא safek d'Oraita
we treat לחומרא, l'chumra, we treat more stringently. יוסי בן יועזר said
in ספק טומאה safek tumah in רשות היחיד reshut hayachid in private
we treat stringently, we say is טמא, but ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים,
safek tumah birshut harabim, a ספק safek of a purity cases which
take place in public are considered leniently or we consider them טהור.
והא הלכתא מסוטה גמרינן לה. v'ha hilcheta miSotah gamrinan lah. We learn
it from סוטה. Sotah. Okay. מה סוטה רשות היחיד? ma Sotah reshut
hayachid? So just like a case of סוטה, Sotah, right? The seclusion,
this woman goes into a private place with this with her lover,
אף טומאה רשות היחיד. af tumah reshut hayachid. So טומאה tumah also
because the word that's used in the פרשה parsha of סוטה Sotah
is always הוטמאה. hutma'a. She became טמאה. tmeia. She was involved in
this impure relationship that's a violation of the marriage. So because that
only can take place in private, but סוטה Sotah is a doubtful
case, right? We only have suspicion, we only have implications, but no
actual testimony. So too, ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah birshut hayachid
is טמא. We still has consequences. So that's, it's learned by an
abstraction from the laws of טומאה. tumah? הא אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה
ואין מורין כן. ha amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha v'ein morin kein. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, yes, that's the הלכה halacha but we don't
teach it that way, we don't tell people that, because we don't
want people relying on the leniency of ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים safek
tumah birshut harabim to that oh, every every doubtful case, right? So
you'll imagine that a case that really isn't doubtful is doubtful and
then you're going to end up being lenient about something that would
really be טמא. ואתא איהו ואורי לה. v'ata ihu v'ori lah. And
then he, that is, until יוסי בן יועזר it had been... הלכה
ואין מורין כן halacha ve'ein morin kein that you shouldn't teach it
in public cause people will make mistakes and ואתא איהו Yose ben
Yoezer came ואורי ליה ve'orei lei אורויי oruyei and he taught it
in public. That is, he publicized this principle ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים
safek tumah birshut harabim is טהור because they said הלכתא גמירי לה
hilcheta gemiri lah it's learned from the principle of סוטה, Sotah, it's
some kind of an ancient הלכה halacha or הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe miSinai maybe that this principle exists. So how could you say
oh he instituted it? No no no, it was that they used
to keep it private so people wouldn't make mistakes and then he
started publicizing it. Okay. תני נמי הכי Tani nami hachi we have
a ברייתא braita that supports this. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer
כורות נתצה להם. korot natza lahem. He banged the boards together. ואמר
עד כאן רשות הרבים עד כאן רשות היחיד. Ve'amar ad kan reshut
harabim ad kan reshut hayachid. He said here's where's רשות הרבים reshut
harabim and here's רשות היחיד reshut hayachid like he made some kind
of a separation. כי אתו לקמיה דרבי ינאי Ki atu l'kamei d'Rabbi
Yannai when they came before רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai אמר להו amar
lehu המייא דשיקעתא ha'maya d'shik'ata and they asked רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
the water of שיקעתא? shik'ata? It's like from a like from a
stream or from a ditch, right? No? Yeah, דבנהרא, d'vinahra, the שיקעתא
דבנהרא, shik'ata d'vinahra, the ditch by the river, זילו טבולו. zilu tevulu.
And he said, so it was some kind of a doubtful case
about this מקוה, mikveh, but because it's in a רשות הרבים, reshut
harabim, he said זילו טבולו, zilu tevulu, go and go to the
מקוה. mikveh. That is, you could use it as a מקוה. mikveh.
That's very interesting, 'cause that's not about ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים, safek
tumah birshut harabim, that's about a ספק safek of a kosher מקוה
mikveh in רשות הרבים reshut harabim seemingly. So this question comes up
very much in the first פרק perek of נדה, Niddah, question of
if you have, right, if you're טמא, you have a חזקת טומאה
chezkas tumah and now want to remove the טומאה tumah by going
to the מקוה. mikveh. Can I rely on a ספק מקוה safek
mikveh in order to purify me from my טומאה? Maybe not. Even
though I have the principle ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים, safek tumah birshut
harabim, 'cause I already have a standing, my current status is טמא.
To remove the טומאה status I need something that's a sure thing
to get me out of it. So that comes up and a
big סוגיא sugya at the beginning of נדה Niddah about a מקוה
mikveh that had a drip and you don't know how at what
point in the מקוה mikveh had dropped below 40 סאה se'ah that
you have a ספק, safek, can you rely on that or not?
Charlie. So דבנהרא d'vinahra which presumably is a river. Ah, but it's
a שיקעתא, shik'ata, it's the ditch next to the river, right? You
can't טבילה tevila in a river is a whole other question. It
comes up extensively in תוספות Tosafot and and there's a very long
ר"ן Ran in נדרים, Nedarim, I think it's somewhere around דף מ"ם-ish
daf mem in נדרים, Nedarim, very like three page ר"ן Ran about
this and and basically the quick summary is there's lots of problems
that could potentially be a problem טבילה tevila in a river because
it's moving, because because if it's moving it's a problem if it's
rainwater. Rainwater is only מטהר metaher if it's stationary. And there's a
problem that it's out in public so you're going to be afraid
of people seeing you, so you're going to rush. And because there's
a problem of mud at the riverbed. So all of those three
problems the different ראשונים Rishonim address in different ways and it's extensively
discussed. Generally not recommended. A lake or the ocean is much better
'cause it at least deals with some of those issues more than
others. A question would extend presumably to tidal estuaries? Like tidal estuaries,
like the Hudson River? Well the Hudson River is an interesting question.
It's not really a river. It's a fjord all the way up
to York New- well the Hudson River is a fjord all the
way up to Troy, New York is a- York New York? York?
Troy! Not York. All the way up to Troy, the Hudson River
has tides. It goes up and back, it flows both directions every
day. So actually it's not so much of a river, right? It's
funny also because I remember I took a trip to Nova Scotia
and they have this thing in Bay of Fundy they say, oh
the Bay of Fundy is a fjord. It's not a fjord. The
Hudson River is a fjord. So anyway, okay. והשלוקות. Ve'hashlukos. Oh, such
a good סוגיא. sugya. Okay. We have a few more minutes we
could do שלוקות. shlukos. We can at least start it. Okay. So
והשלוקות, Ve'hashlukos, the משנה Mishnah had said one of the other prohibited
foods of עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim was their שלוקות. shlukos. So what
are שלוקות? shlukos? So שלוקות, shlukos, the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot
says that ברכה bracha on שלוקות shlukos is a bit of a
debate, should be האדמה. ha'adama. שלוקות shlukos is a vegetable soup that's
made out of the vegetables and then you took the vegetables out.
Right? Like you boiled vegetables in water, extract all the flavor and
then you took the vegetables out. So the ברכה bracha is still
האדמה, ha'adama, that's the הלכה, halacha, but but it's a debate in
the סוגיא sugya in ברכות Berachot whether it should be שהכל shehakol
or האדמה. ha'adama. And ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a different take. And ירושלמי
Yerushalmi has different- but ירושלמי Yerushalmi always has a different take Charlie.
The point is that שלוקות shlukos is some kind of a cooked
food. Now the question, what we're this הלכה halacha for us is
usually called בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, foods cooked by non-Jews. It's interesting
that in the משנה Mishnah specifically they referred to שלוקות, shlukos, specific
example, which is number one interesting. Number two is if it's a
question of oh you know, foods cooked by non-Jews, what would you
immediately think the problem would be? כשרות. Kashrut. You would think that
oh because maybe they put something טרף treif in and I don't
know about it. That that would be the most intuitive reason. So
what we're going to address here is the concern. So what we're
going to address here is the concern of the דאורייתא problem of
non-kosher ingredients compared to also the דרבנן rule. There's actually a rule
against foods cooked by non-Jews even if you're sure that all the
ingredients are kosher. So let's see this inside. Maybe poison or something
given the context? Poison, we haven't had poison for a few days
now, now we've shifted. It made an impression on me. Okay, it
made an impression, it's an important discussion. Maybe also the socializing? And
the so, well, yeah, we'll see. Actually, let's just start from this
from tomorrow because it is 8:30. Hope everyone has a great day,
we'll pick up here,
מיכאל Michoel will pick up from here tomorrow. Okay, have a wonderful
day. Bye-bye.